Hey guys, in this video, we will be
looking
at some more advanced and harder problems
for
kinematics. So last time in last video,
I've
explained things slowly, but this time
I'll
be going way faster. So if you still
aren't
really familiar with those questions, feel
free
to ask me to release more videos or find
some
videos yourself to watch and learn.
So a ball is thrown upwards from the
ground
at a speed of 25 metres per second.
At the same instance, another ball is
dropped
from rest from a building 30 metres high.
How many seconds will the two balls be at
the
same height? Okay, let's see.
So, let's visualize it in a way where
they're
on the same x-axis. So what do I mean by
that?
Well, this is ball 1 being dropped and
this
is ball 2 being launched. So this bottom
ball
is going upwards at a speed of 25 metres
per
second. And this top ball is dropped from
rest,
so the initial velocity is just 0 metres
per
second. And it's dropped at a height of 30
metres,
so I'll do 30 metres high.
And what will happen is basically this
ball
is going to go down and this ball is going
to
go up until they meet at this point.
Let's call this point P.
And we need to know how long it takes for
them
to do it. Keep in mind that they both take
the
same time to get to point P because since
they
meet at point P, they take the same time
to
get to point P. So what I want to do for
this
question is I want to give both equations
a
kinematic formula in terms of its distance
travelled
and time.
Because let's say this distance travelled
is
d1 and this distance travelled is d2.
Well, we know that d1 plus d2 is equal to
30,
right? Because when they meet, this is
going
down from 30, this is going up from 30, so
d1
plus d2 equals 30 at point P.
So we need to express each balls, we need
to
express d1 in terms of t and d2 in terms
of
t. So d1 is for ball number 1, so let's
get
started on that. Looking at this formula
sheet,
I see three equations I can use, but the
one
that stands out to me the most for this
question
that is applicable for this question is
this
one. Don't worry if you can't spot it
right
away, when I was starting, it took me one
or
two minutes to actually find the equation
first,
but after practice, you'll get used to it.
Yeah, it's the right equation. So, let's
express
d1. Let's first write down the raw
equation.
x equals x0 plus v0 vx0 t plus 1 over 2
ax t squared. Keep in mind that
acceleration
for everything, for both balls, is
negative
10 metres per second squared, or negative
9.81,
but I'll use negative 10. Don't forget
it's
negative because acceleration is going
down.
And now let's modify this equation so that
we
can use it for our equation. So, let's do
it
in blue, because this one's blue. Well, d1
is
x, because x is the distance traveled, or
x
is here. So, x
should actually be d2, because at point P,
x
will be at d2. So, d2 equals, and
x0 is just 30, because it starts at 30
metres,
plus vx0. Well, it's being dropped at a
speed
of 0 metres per second, it's being dropped
from
rest. So, this is just 0, so this whole
thing
is just 0, and 1 over 2, gravity,
negative 10, t squared.
So, d2 equals 30 minus 5t squared.
I wouldn't factor it for now, because
we're
going to be using another equation to
solve
for t, but we will see if we need to do
that
later. And for this one, we have initial
velocity,
we have t, we have d2, and yeah.
So, since we have those values, we can
also
use the same equation as we did last time,
so
this equation. So, I'll be doing ball 1,
and
ball 2.
But sometimes, you might have to use
different
equations, if there is another case.
Well, we know that the ball's position is
also
d2, because at point P, both of them are
at
this position, which is d2. Well,
x-initial is
0, because it starts on the ground, which
is
y equals 0. The original velocity is 25
times
t, plus 1 over 2, the acceleration is
still
gravity, which is negative 10, t squared.
And now you get d2 equals 25t minus
5t squared. And now we can just
solve for t. Since both of them are
describing
t2s, we can just set those equal.
Just sub in one equation into the other,
simple
math. So, since d2 equals d2, we can use
this
one. 30 minus 5t squared equals 25t minus
5t
squared. And now let's factor out 5, so we
get
6 minus t squared equals 5t minus t
squared.
Add t squared on both sides, so 6 equals
5t,
and you'll get t equals 6 over 5.
And when you do that, 6 over 5 is 1.2, I
believe.
My brain is not breathing. Yep, 1.2
seconds.
And that will be your answer. They will be
at
the same height after 1.2 seconds.
So, a car accelerates from rest
along a straight road with an acceleration
of
2 metres per second squared. And you want
to
know how fast it will be moving after it
has
traveled 100 metres. Well, you know the
acceleration
is obviously 2 metres per second squared,
positive,
because this question, it's an easier
question,
we're just dealing with a one-dimensional
question.
And you want to know the final velocity.
You know the initial velocity is equal to
0,
because it accelerates from rest. Let's
say
the initial distance is 0, because it's
starting
at a distance of 0 from the starting
point.
And you know, that's all you know, I
think.
So, looking at these formulas...
Oh, sorry, I didn't see that it has
traveled
100 metres. I was so confused. So, you
know,
it has traveled 100 metres. So, the final
position
will be 100 metres. And now you can
actually
see that you can use this formula, because
you
have all those values for that formula.
So,
let's just list it out. vx squared equals
vx
naught squared plus 2ax x minus
x-initial. And v of x squared, that's the
final
velocity, so that's what we want to find.
So,
let's just isolate for it. v of x is the
same
thing as v of f. It's just the square root
of
the whole thing. And now, you just
plug in all the numbers. This is a really
simple
question. The square root of the initial
velocity
is 0, because it starts from rest, plus 2.
The initial acceleration is 2. x minus
x-initial
is just 100 minus 0, which is 100.
And you can take this 2 out, and 100 is 10
squared,
so you get 2 times 10. And then you get 20
metres
per second, which is your final velocity,
how
fast it will be moving after it has
traveled
100 metres. And that's how you solve this
question.
So, yeah, that's all for these examples.
I hope you have learned something, and I
hope
this was useful. Thank you!